Guide to the Congregation Beth Am (Or Ami) records, 1978-2022 MS 733
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Congregation Beth Am (Or Ami) Records
1978-2022
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Congregation Beth Am (Houston, Tex)
MS 733
1.75 Linear Feet 2 boxes
The collection consists of one box of correspondence, event materials, news clippings, newsletters, and institutional records such as, committee meeting minutes, speeches, and fundraising materials from Congregation Beth Am between 1978 and 2022 and an oral history with Rabbi Gideon Estes in 2020.
Biographical / Historical
On October 12, 1972, a group of young Jewish people met for the first time in the Kendall Branch Public Library on Memorial Drive to discuss the possibility of starting a Congregation to serve the needs of the increasing number of Jewish families settling in the Memorial-Northwest area of Houston. The need for a West Houston synagogue was recognized at that first meeting.
Interest in forming a synagogue spread quickly and by January 1973, seventy people had already formed committees, held a Hanukkah service and agreed that a religious school was a necessity.
the first Board election was held in April 1973, and that month the members voted to become a conservative congregation. Within a six-month period both a Sisterhood and a Men's Club were formed, an ark was built to house the newly acquired Torah and Rabbi Irwin Halpern became the congregation's first spiritual leader and school administrator. Jerard Y. Cohen became the first President of the congregation.
In 1975 Beth Am purchased a facility on Brittmoore Road. As the membership continued to grow a new sanctuary, kitchen, and offices were added. The youth group, Beth Am Synagogue Youth, was also created around this time.
As the years passed the members decided that further growth was hampered by the somewhat industrial location of the synagogue. As a part of that decision, Congregation Beth Am merged with Congregation Or Hadash in 2001 and became Congregation Or Ami.
Sandra Block was elected president of Congregation Beth Am in the 1979.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, event materials, meeting minutes, written histories of the congregation, an oral history with Rabbi Gideon Estes, newsletters, news clippings, speeches, and a directory document some of the events and activities undertaken by members of Congregation Beth Am -- including Sandra Block while she was president of the Congregation -- from 1978 to 2022. Of particular interest are the written histories of the congregation in materials donated by both Sandra Block and the institution.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials donated by Sandra Block March 2018, and Rabbi Gideon Estes May 2019 and 2020.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection were donated by the institution and by Sandra Block and have been arranged in two series as follows:
Series I: Institutional Materials; Series II: Sandra Block institution records; Series III: Oral Histories; Series IV: Addenda
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life; LGBTQ people
Document Types
Records (documents); Correspondence; Programs (Publications); newsletters; directories; Oral histories
- Series I: Institution Materials, 1973-2005
  - Subseries I: Correspondence, 1985-07-13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subseries II: Event Materials, 1979-2005
    - Beth Am B'nai Mitzvah Dedication program, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Installation of Rabbi Barry Baron, 1991-12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Beth Am 20th Anniversary Celebration materials, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Beth Am dinner/dance/auction honoring Aaron Stehr, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Prayer book for Friday evening services, Congregation Or Ami, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries III: Institutional Records, 1987
    - Membership meeting minutes, 1987-09-09 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Beth Am/Or Hadash/Or Ami Congregation History, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subseries IV: Newsletters/News clippings, 1973-1987
    - Beth Am "Communications" newsletters, vol. 1-2, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Beth Am "Communications" newsletters. vol. 2-3, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Beth Am "Communications" newsletter, vol. 3, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - News clippings re: new Rabbi and new members, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II: Sandra Block institution records, 1978-1984
  - Congregation Beth Am: A History, c. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Welcome packet for new members, Congregation Beth Am, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letter to committee chairs, Congregation Beth Am, 1977-10-28 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - B'nai Mitzvah Committee documents, Beth Am, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sandra Block, presidential installation speech, Beth Am, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Program for construction, Congregation Beth Am, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Architecture committee documents, Beth Am, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Beth Am Ritual Committee notes on aliyot, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sandra Block's remarks delivered at the 10th anniversary celebration of congregation Beth Am, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Telephone directory, Congregation Beth Am, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fundraising booklet for new Beth Am building, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series III: Oral Histories
  - Rabbi Gideon Estes oral history interview and transcript, 2020-05-25
- Series IV: Addenda
  - Rabbi Estes' "coming out" story delivered to Congregation Beth Am, 2015-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Services conducted during Covid pandemic, 2020-2021 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Invocation given to Harris County Commissioner's Court, 2020-10-13 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Outsmart magazine with article on Rabbi Estes, 2020-12 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Bulletins / Newsletters / Booklet, 1995-2022 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Materials used in services during the Covid-19 pandemic, 2022 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Signage used during Covid Zoom services, 2020-2022 (Box 2, Folder 1)